<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The journey of a restless mind</title>
    <description>A personal blog about my experience as a resident apprentice at 8th Light
</description>
    <link>http://demonh3x.github.io//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://demonh3x.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 17:09:52 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 17:09:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Estimating</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;To assign tasks we are doing iteration planning meetings (IPMs). In those, we specify which tasks I have to do next. The tracking of those tasks is done in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban_board&quot;&gt;kanban board&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I have to estimate how much time I think they are going to take. The time units are half day of work. That means that 2 units are a full day of work (8 hours). The time units are not dividable. And an estimation can’t be 0 time units. That estimation is based on 3 points of view:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being optimistic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being realistic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being pessimistic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am noticing that maybe I am being pessimistic by default. 
Optimistic, realistic and pessimistic seem subjective thoughts. I can’t estimate with subjective thoughts, they are unreliable. So I have to find a more objective way of thinking about it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To achieve that task, what are the steps I have to take?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do I have some experience in some of the steps? How much time did they take?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optimistic: Everything goes really smooth, there are no interruptions, full focus on the task…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Realistic: Considering some interruptions, some moments when one can’t focus properly, maybe I missed one or two steps to complete the task…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pessimistic: I got my assumptions wrong. There are missed steps to complete the task that I did not think of. I am being interrupted often. I can’t focus on the task. I will dedicate out-of-work time to keep up…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of thinking pessimistically that way is that my estimations are very exaggerated.
I had to think about it from other point of view: It should not take more than X time to do it.
Thinking of it that way made me value the time I was spending in a task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand. If I have never done anything similar enough to the step I’m trying to estimate, How am I supposed to know the time is going to take to do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel really uncomfortable estimating, that means I need to improve on it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://demonh3x.github.io//8thlight/2015/03/06/estimating.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://demonh3x.github.io//8thlight/2015/03/06/estimating.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>8thlight</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Optimizing the communication</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This entry is about this week’s task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task consisted in being able to do the &lt;code&gt;Coin Changer&lt;/code&gt; kata driven by tests in Ruby and using Vim. All of that under 7 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard once a person say: “Those craftsmen/craftswomen doing katas super-fast only want to show off. That practice is completely pointless.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to do this task, you need to communicate with the computer efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I introduce next the &lt;code&gt;Abstract concept&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;An analogy&lt;/code&gt; about communicating. You can skip those parts and go to &lt;code&gt;Analyzing the task’s aspects&lt;/code&gt; section if you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract-concept&quot;&gt;Abstract concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a sender wants to communicate some information to a receiver, some prerequisites need to exist for that communication to be successful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sender needs to know clearly the information he/she wants to communicate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They both need to be able to understand and express ideas with a common language.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As important as the details of the language are, the speed at which both parts can communicate is also important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-analogy&quot;&gt;An analogy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets put the Spanish spoken language as an analogy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the speaker doesn’t know what he/she wants to communicate, there is no point in trying to speak in any language. The more concise the information is, the better. When the speaker uses too many words to say something, he/she may create confusion to the listener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The details of the language may vary depending on the zone it is spoken.
It is not exactly the same Spanish spoken in Madrid than the one spoken in Mexico city.
If there is a word that means one thing in Madrid another thing in Mexico city, and you want a perfect communication, the speaker and the listener need to know which meaning they are referring to when using that word. Otherwise there is going to be confusion. 
If they notice something was confused, solving that confusion (if they can) really slows down the communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed at which a person can understand spoken Spanish might be a problem.
If the speaker is forced to speak too slow or the listener needs the speaker to repeat the message too many times, the speaker can become frustrated and even stop trying to communicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed at which a person can speak Spanish is also a limiting factor. 
It is quite difficult if the speaker’s head thinks faster than his/her mouth can articulate words.
Even worse: it is really frustrating when the speaker wants to say something but can’t find the words and combine them to say that thing precisely. The best he/she can do in that case is to say something somewhat similar hoping that the receiver understands the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precision at which a person can speak Spanish is another important thing to consider.
The person might be, for example, stuttering when speaking Spanish. That makes him/her to be constantly correcting himself/herself and take more time than usual to say something. It could also confuse the listener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;analyzing-the-tasks-aspects&quot;&gt;Analyzing the task’s aspects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I introduced the analogy because it has a lot of similarities with the process I faced doing this task. I will explain them as they appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this task, there are many aspects to develop. Lets identify them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understanding, solving and simplifying the problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ruby syntax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TDD&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vim usage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those aspects are ordered by their priority in the objective of achieving the task.
It does not make sense to learn Ruby syntax if you don’t know how to face the problem yet.
It does not make sense to learn RSpec (to do TDD) if you don’t know the Ruby syntax yet.
It does not make sense to use another text editor to go faster if you are struggling with the problem, with the Ruby syntax or with the TDD procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean you have to master each aspect before getting into the next one. It only means that improving a previous aspect has more time profit than improving on following ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;understanding-solving-and-simplifying-the-problem&quot;&gt;Understanding, solving and simplifying the problem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets start by understand what is the problem we are trying to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is about calculating the optimal combination of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coins_of_the_pound_sterling#Coins_in_circulation&quot;&gt;UK coins&lt;/a&gt; for a money amount. Optimal means that the bigger coins are preferred. The notes are not considered. For example: given £5.98, the coins should be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two £2 coins&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £1 coin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £0.50 coin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two £0.20 coins&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £0.05 coin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £0.02 coin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A £0.01 coin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/demonh3x/2f41e9ce5ae0897e0e00&quot;&gt;one of my firsts solutions&lt;/a&gt; I introduced some &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/79106557&quot;&gt;accidental complication&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought the problem needed the notes to be considered. I did not understand the problem. By not considering them I simplified the problem and saved some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made a class with an instance method. That method did not depend on any state of the instance. The result only depends on the parameter. By defining that function without a class I simplified the problem and saved some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used floating point numbers for the coins. That has problems with precision which I solved using BigDecimal. By using integers instead of floating point numbers I simplified the problem and saved some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Going back to the analogy: this is knowing what I want to say and being concise doing it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ruby-syntax&quot;&gt;Ruby syntax&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ruby syntax is similar to other programming languages but it has it peculiarities. I needed to know which differences has and what they mean before continuing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Going back to the analogy: this is specifying that we are going to use the Madrid’s Spanish instead of Mexico’s.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interactive_Ruby_Shell&quot;&gt;irb&lt;/a&gt; is a great tool to learn the ruby syntax and to experiment with it. 
The more familiarized you are with the syntax, the faster you can express what you want. By searching in the documentation, experimenting and practicing I became more familiar with the syntax and faster writing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Going back to the analogy: this is finding the words and combining them properly to say that thing precisely.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coding style is another thing to keep in mind if you don’t want to create confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;tdd&quot;&gt;TDD&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TDD here is a communication enhancer. It makes the communication from the computer to you go much faster. Instead of running the code, trying the different combinations and checking manually, you have all the features tested automatically. You just have to run the tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That makes the computer tell you if you are doing something wrong, what are you doing wrong and when you are doing it wrong. 
You can go back a bit and try to do it differently. 
That is quite grumpy, isn’t it? It would be interesting if the computer also suggested valid alternatives, but that is out of my knowledge and seems &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ianbach/status/564938305251192832&quot;&gt;magical&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed of the communication between the programmer and the computer is the time difference between the moment you write code and the computer tells you everything is OK.
The more frequent you run the tests, the faster the communication is.
By automating the execution of the tests after saving, I made the communication faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I would need to improve this, I would follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KentBeck/status/570682400948260864&quot;&gt;Kent’s suggestion&lt;/a&gt; by running the tests each time a key is pressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Going back to the analogy: this is making the listener to understand and respond faster.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.8thlight.com/uncle-bob/2013/05/27/TheTransformationPriorityPremise.html&quot;&gt;transformation priority premise&lt;/a&gt; suggests you do the steps that require less effort first. By doing that, the code was evolving smoother and faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;vim-usage&quot;&gt;Vim usage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, if you are really comfortable with the previous aspects, the text editor may get in the way of transmitting the information to the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning to use vim feels counterintuitive. Just to get as productive in vim as in your current text editor, you have to learn a lot of shortcuts and be comfortable with the modes. That takes time and practice.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://vim-adventures.com/&quot;&gt;Vim Adventures&lt;/a&gt; is an interesting way to learn it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is writing in vim faster than in a graphical text editor? That’s because all the shortcuts are as easy to press as any letter. That makes your hands not to lose time moving to the mouse or arrows and then lose more time going back to the writing position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Going back to the analogy: this is making your mouth articulate words faster to keep up with the thoughts in your head.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to be careful to learn properly the  actions. Because if you learn that moving a finger to press a key to do an action, but that key doesn’t do that action, you are going to be correcting yourself very often and losing time because of it. By polishing my finger moves I saved some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Going back to the analogy: this is stuttering while trying to say something.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/121234763&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;313&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/121234763&quot;&gt;Coin Changer Kata&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/user33522377&quot;&gt;Mateu Adsuara&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s 5 minutes 15 seconds. And there is yet room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember: 
&lt;code&gt;Strive for progress, not perfection&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://demonh3x.github.io//8thlight/vim/ruby/kata/2015/03/05/optimizing-the-communication.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://demonh3x.github.io//8thlight/vim/ruby/kata/2015/03/05/optimizing-the-communication.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>8thlight</category>
        
        <category>vim</category>
        
        <category>ruby</category>
        
        <category>kata</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why to write a blog?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the first things that is requested in a Resident apprenticeship is to have a personal blog about the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to write a blog before. I wanted some kind of reference for anyone interested in my work and the things I do.
Maybe I was looking at it with the wrong perspective. A blog may not only be for others to read, but for oneself to improve by consciously expressing the thoughts, expand knowledge or explore new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But is not easy to have the perseverance to keep writing content. 
Perseverance is tricky to get. It can be thought as managing one’s limited willpower. Perseverance is similar to having a habit. There is going to be times when one doesn’t feel like doing what needs to be done or there are better things to do. But not doing what needs to be done when that happens is the worst decision. At least do a bit of what you need to do just to get used to doing it regularly. It is also important not to burnout doing it. Try to feel when you are getting tired of doing it and rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also not easy to have a continuous repertoire of subjects. I’m currently writing down the main ideas I want to talk about. That enables me to expand them when I need to create a post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://demonh3x.github.io//8thlight/blog/perseverance/2015/03/05/why-to-write-a-blog.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://demonh3x.github.io//8thlight/blog/perseverance/2015/03/05/why-to-write-a-blog.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>8thlight</category>
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>perseverance</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Restless</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was my first day at 8th Light London as a Resident Apprentice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is Monday. I arrived Saturday night (around 2am) to a hostel I booked that is 20 minutes walking from the office. 
That night was awful. I was sharing the room with other 11 people who wanted a place to fall asleep after partying nearby. That means: drunk people making noise until 4/5am.
Next Sunday I had to wake up somewhat early to get a phone number and be able to communicate with anyone sharing flats. I spent most of the day looking and contacting adverts. I got time to view a couple of rooms. I was needed to stay active communicating until late in the evening.
Although I was expected to be at 9am at the office, I had to wake up a bit earlier to be able to go to a bank and try to get one account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those things got me really mentally tired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was being &lt;code&gt;restless&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always considered myself a restless person in the meaning of &lt;code&gt;non-stop learning, doing and improving everything I&#39;ve been interested in&lt;/code&gt;. I didn’t want the other meanings of the word: &lt;code&gt;worried&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;nervous&lt;/code&gt;. It’s funny how the word &lt;code&gt;restless&lt;/code&gt; is composed by the words &lt;code&gt;rest&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;less&lt;/code&gt;, like saying: &lt;code&gt;You are resting too much, You don&#39;t need to rest&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets continue with my experience of the first day at 8th Light. 
I received a nice, warm welcome from a lot of people at 8th Light. They very kindly offered help with anything I need in this transition. I really appreciate that! Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some necessary paperwork, I got assigned some tasks in which there is the writing of this blog. I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; for it.
I struggled to concentrate and understand the basics of it because I was mentally tired. I was spending too much time for something as basic as creating a blog. Around 2 to 4 times longer than I think I would have spent if I were properly rested. To minimize the amount of wasted time because of my tiredness I decided to copy, paste and edit the built-in starting template instead of properly learning the tool. I thought: &lt;code&gt;I just need to create a basic blog to start posting. I will improve it if and when needed&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same situation happened with the following tasks… I wasn’t able to concentrate. I made bad decisions that I realized afterwards and had to go back to fix them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I sleep well, and all I need, I can feel much more mentally agile.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://demonh3x.github.io//8thlight/mentalhealth/2015/03/02/restless.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://demonh3x.github.io//8thlight/mentalhealth/2015/03/02/restless.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>8thlight</category>
        
        <category>mentalhealth</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Jekyll!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Tom&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints &amp;#39;Hi, Tom&amp;#39; to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll-help&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s dedicated Help repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 13:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://demonh3x.github.io//jekyll/update/2015/03/02/example.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://demonh3x.github.io//jekyll/update/2015/03/02/example.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
